# 这个豆子很怪啊
Soybeans are weird
# 今年子的豆子
Say we harvest some beans in this year
# 明年不打完到了后年打起没得豆花得
If we don’t grind them by the next year, we can’t make any tofu pudding from them later
# 就有那么怪
They are just so weird
# 不怕你（豆子）还焦干的都是这个样子
It doesn’t matter whether they are fresh or dried. Both are like that
# 不是我们把它泡点来推豆花嘛
So, how about soaking them and making some tofu pudding?
# 可以啊
Sounds good
# 这个豆子是好久的啊
When were these beans harvested?
# 去年的
Last year
# 去年好久的
When in the last year?
# 去年子收豆子的时候撒
Last year when harvesting soybeans
# 一般收豆子是6-7月都嘛
Soybeans are usually harvested in June and July
# 这个黄豆已经1年多了很多都生了虫
These soybeans have been stored for over a year. Some already have worms
# 为了不浪费呢今天把它做成豆花儿
To avoid wasting, today we’ll make them into a tofu pudding
# 我们富顺的千年古菜豆花儿
Tofu pudding, a dish in Fushun with a thousand years of history
# 走嘛先拿去泡起嘛
Let’s go, soak them first
# 要得
Sure
# 泡2个小时哦
Soak for two hours
# 嗯
Yeah
# 我要练功了我的蛤蟆功
It’s my training time. My “hamagong” (“toad-style martial arts”)
# 蛤蟆功
“Hamagong”
# 我们这个豆子泡了几个小时终于泡好了用冷水发的这个
We’ve finally done soaking the soybeans after a few hours. In cold water
# 但是还是有些硬的
But they are still a bit hard
# 有
Yeah
# 等我伯爷把这个袖套戴起了之后我要
After uncle puts on the oversleeves
# 磨豆花儿
I’m gonna grind the soybeans
# 练功了
Training time
# 嘿嘿 练功来了
Hehe, training time
# 这个是练功哦
This is training for real
# 好了现在我们要推豆花了
Alright, now we are gonna grind the beans
# 先放
Load it first
# 是朝这边撒
In this direction?
# 是朝这边
In this direction
# 现在这个白色的浆已经出来了
Now the white liquid is coming out
# 这个你别说还挺累人的
You know what, this is actually quite exhausting
# 磨这个要马步要扎好
To grind it, you need to make a perfect “Mabu” (“horse-riding stance”)
# 腰要挺直
keep the lower back straight
# 这个手要用力
and apply the force with your arm
# 我这样磨了一会儿
I’ve been grinding for a while
# 都有一点
Now I’m a bit...
# 累不累呀
Are you tired?
# 累
Yes
# 当然累
Tired, of course
# 别人都说打的（机器）没有磨的（手工磨）好吃
I heard that those ground by a machine are less tasty than those by hands
# 我也觉得磨的（手工磨）好吃
I think so, hand ground ones are better
# 磨的肯定好吃啊
It’s surely better to grind with hands
# 机器磨的速度快 手工磨的是慢慢磨的
Machines grind too fast. We grind slowly with hands
# 这个石磨磨出来的有一股清香味
There’s a refreshing fragrance from this stone grind
# 现在都可以闻得到
Now we can already smell it
# 如果是机器打的话它就是
If it’s ground by a machine
# 机器打的就没有这个清香味
there’s no such refreshing fragrance
# 就像你说的机器打的管的你得不得行都给你打过去
Like you said, a machine grinds everything, both good and bad
# 这个是慢慢磨的
This one grinds slowly
# 然后这个石磨磨的话它不行的东西它出来了之后
And if a bad bean enters the stone grind, after it passes
# 它不会磨碎
it won’t be ground
# 就会更那个渣一起出来
it goes out together with the soy pulp
# 你在外面吃的豆花用的什么来点的（制作）
What (coagulant) do they use to make tofu at other places?
# 石膏都嘛
Gypsum
# 石膏点的好吃过屁还是要我们这个胆水的
Gypsum tofu is not tasty at all. They need our “danshui”
(A chloride solution obtained from local salt mines)
# 外面没得办法得只能这样子
They have to. They don’t have danshui at their places
# 胆水点的吃起口感都不一样
Danshui tofu tastes completely different in your mouth # 这里避免使用 “texture”，四伯说话没那么文
# 香味味道都不一样
The smell and the taste are different
# 是嘛
Right
# 不是
I mean...
# 这样磨起吃起多安逸安
Grind it like this. It tastes so nice
# 不是工具人来 工具人
I mean, where’s my “tool person”? Come here
# 工具人来磨
Come and grind it, “tool person”
# 这个我都搞累了
This makes me so tired
# 这样子朝这边不要磨反了
In this direction. Not the other way
# 试一下看
I’ll try
# 我手都磨红了
My hands are sworn and red
# 要戴手套
You need gloves
# 叫兄弟来帮忙
Should have asked my bro for some help
# 兄弟在养竹鼠
My bro is raising bamboo rats
# 泼来当蘸水噶 嗯
- Making dipping sauce?
- Yeah
# 轻点哈
Careful
# 好
Yeah
# 多放点柴一会儿就烧开了
Add more firewood. It boils in a while
# 这个豆浆老香了
This soy milk smells so good
# 这个
This one
# 手磨的豆浆
Hand-ground soy milk
# 泡子不管它是不是
Just leave the foam there, right?
# 等会儿要散
It will be gone later
# 一会儿它要散开了就要散
It will be gone later. After it boils
# 要这个才得行娃儿嘞
This is needed
# 才好才方便点
so that it’s more convenient
# 我们这个把它卷好了待会儿把豆浆直接倒进去
We first wrap it, and then pour the soy milk into it
# 剩下的渣就滤在这个里面来了
The soy pulp will be filtered and left inside
# 然后里面的那个浆再烧开了就可以当豆浆喝了
Then we can drink the soy milk after boiling it again
# 这个非常浓的
This is very thick
# 好香哦这个
It smells so good
# 我还是觉得 哎呀太幸福了
I’m like, wow, what a joyful life!
# 幸福的味道
The taste of joy
# 这是我们剩下的渣滓把它
This is the soy pulp
# 把剩下的这个
Let’s press out
# 豆浆挤出来
all the soy milk left there
# 嘿 （用）这个挤还可以
Huh, this press is good
# 是不哦
Is it?
# 嗯 比你瓜瓢还得行
Hmm, better than your gourd
# 现在把里面的豆浆全部给它榨出来
Now we extract all the soy milk from it
# 这个剩的豆渣可以拿来喂猪
The soy pulp can be used to feed the pigs
# 还可以拿来做一个菜
or be made into a dish
# 慢点哈不要一下倒出去了
Careful, don’t pour too fast
# 别看这里一锅没多少
It doesn’t seem too much in this wok
# 可能有40多斤
but there’s actually over 40 jin probably (jin = 500g)
# 40-50斤的样子
40-50 jin
# 这个豆浆是我们刚刚弄出来的我先尝一口
This is our freshly made soy milk. Let me try it
# 豆浆味特别重
A strong soy milk flavor
# 伯爷尝不尝一下
Wanna try, uncle?
# 我就尝哈嘛
Yeah, I’ll try
# 反正这都是我们喝得拿着喝就是
Since it’s just us, we just take and drink (with the wok spoon)
# 嗯 这个就比你那个机子打那个豆浆喝起香啊
Hmm, this tastes better than the machine-ground soy milk
# 嗯
Yeah
# 这个就有点特别 我跟你说
This is quite special, you know
# 等会儿你点（豆花）吗伯娘点哦
Are you going to dip it (with the “danshui”), or aunt?
# 你伯娘点 你伯娘点豆花得行还是可以
Your aunt. She’s good at it
# 这个要一点点的加
This must be added little by little
# 放胆水要慢慢的点
“Danshui” must be added slowly
# 慢慢的点要好点
Dip it slowly, so that it’s good
# 以前老年人点豆花儿怎么点的呢
How did the elderlies do it in the past?
# 用筷子慢慢点 差不多要一个小时
They used a chopstick to dip it little by little. It took about one hour
# 四伯爷快过来看
Uncle, come here
# 噢哟 得起豆花了
Yo-Ho, it becomes tofu pudding
# 起豆花了
It becomes tofu pudding
# 嗯
Yeah
# 我们这个胆水慢慢一点一点的加
We added the danshui little by little
# 加到现在加了两三次之后开始有这个豆花出来了
After adding for two or three times, it started to turn into tofu pudding
# 它这个边上的水啊它就脱离了跟这个蛋白质
The water has been separated from the protein
# 等下再用筲箕我伯爷用筲箕给它压压压
Later, uncle will use a sieve to press it
# 压成一个小坨就变成了豆花
Press it into a small piece, which is tofu pudding
# 想吃豆腐的话就把它再煮老一点 再压紧一点
If you want tofu, you need to boil it for longer, and press it firmer
# 把这个（gao）水舀一点来丢
Get rid of some of the water
# 水太多了
Too much water
# 伯爷压好了我用这个刀来划一下
Uncle has done pressing it. I’ll slice it with a knife
# 一
One
# 咦 大坨很了哟
Eh, that’s a big slice
# 还要横起划
He’ll also slice horizontally
# 四
Four
# 横起划 划五下就是
Horizontally, make five slices
# 大坨很了不好铲 娃儿埃
It’s hard to take out big pieces
# 边上的有点碎
Those on the edge are a bit broken
# 有些没压到 好嫩哦
- Some are not pressed through
- So tender
# 来 你来端我来铲
You take the bowl, I’ll shovel it out
# 你铲来稀巴烂的
You broke it into a mess
# 好 够了
OK, enough
# 我们这个豆花就做好了
We have done making the tofu pudding
# 现在我来跟大家演示一下怎么吃这个豆花
Now let me show you how to eat it
# 这个就是我们刚刚煮的那个豆花儿
This the the tofu pudding that we just made
# 然后这个蘸水是我伯娘做的
And this is the dipping sauce made by my aunt
# 她做的是个家常 家常手法做的
She made it in the homely style
# 就放了辣椒面
She added only chili powder
# 放了大蒜
garlic
# 放了其他一些调料用那个菜籽油给它泼出来的
and some other ingredients, and scalded with boiling rapeseed oil
# 放了 还放了生辣椒就是小米辣
There’s also raw chili, which is Xiaomila chili
# 现在就是夹点豆花儿放一点点这个
Now we pick up the tofu pudding, and add
# 辣椒酱在上面
a bit of chili sauce on its top
# 然后再放点小葱放点这个鱼香
Add some scallion, and some Yuxiang (herb)
# 下面是饭 就是和着一起吃
There’s rice at the bottom. We eat them together
# 我伯娘调的这个味道重了一些
The sauce by my aunt is kind of strongly flavored
# 但是很符合我们农村的吃法
which is exactly the country style here
# 吃一口豆花喝一碗这个汤
Eat some tofu pudding, and then have some soup
# 这个汤（颜色）有点黄黄的
The soup is a bit yellow
# 它是压这个豆花分解出来的这个水分
It’s the water extracted by pressing the tofu pudding
# 还带有一定的下火（功效）
It also relieves “yeet hay”
# 下一次再跟大家分享做这个蘸水 专业做法
Next time, we’ll share a professional recipe of the dipping sauce
# 因为这个是家常版本的
As this one is the homely version
# 可能跟那个专业的有一些区别
there might be some difference with a professional one
# 好了 今天本期视频就到这里
Alright, that’s all of this video
# 我们要吃饭了
We got to enjoy the meal
# 伯爷吃饭了来
Meal time, uncle!
# 我给你整一碗
I’ll make a bowl for you
# 倒一碗汤喝
Have some soup
# 伯娘呢
Where’s aunt?
# 安逸
Nice
# 喊她过来吃饭了
Tell her it’s meal time